Guide to the Virginia Proctor Powell Florence and Charles Florence Family Papers, 1915-2009 UA.91.1
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Virginia Proctor Powell Florence and Charles Florence Family Papers
1915-2009
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Florence, Virginia Proctor Powell
Dyer, Ervin
Florence, Charles W.
UA.91.1
3.75 Linear Feet
The collection contains correspondence, artifacts, and photographs pertaining to Virginia Proctor Powell Florence (1897–1991) and her husband Charles Wilbur Florence (1890–1974). The Florence's were accomplished University of Pittsburgh alumni and Pittsburgh area natives, who overcame the obstacles to advancement, notably racial discrimination and prejudice, on their way to successful lives and careers. The material dates primarily from the 1910's and 1920's. The records were donated to the University of Pittsburgh by Ervin Dyer, senior staff writer for Pitt Magazine.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Ervin Dyer on July 30, 2009.
Previous Citation
Virginia Proctor Powell Florence and Charles Florence Papers, 1915-2009, UA.91.1, University Archives, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Arrangement
The collection has been arranged into five series.
Series I. Virginia Proctor Powell Florence, 1915-1917
Series II. Charles Florence, 1908-1967
Series III. Photographs, 1910-ca. 1965
Series IV. Ervin Dyer Research Materials, ca. 2005-2009
Series V. Oversized Material, ca. 1909-2008
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Biography/History
Virginia Proctor Powell Florence (1903-1991) is noted for being the first African American woman to graduate from a professional library program. She graduated from the Carnegie Library School, which would become the University of Pittsburgh's School of Library and Information Sciences, in 1923. Over her career Florence worked as a public and school librarian in New York City, Washington, D.C., and Richmond, VA.
Charles W. Florence (1890-1974) spent a career devoted to the education profession as teacher, professor, dean, and college president. After growing up and attending high school in Brownsville, Pennsylvania, Florence attended Southwestern State Normal School (present day California University of Pennsylvania) and Storer College before arriving at the University of Pittsburgh. As an undergraduate, Florence captained the University of Pittsburgh's debate team (ca. 1915-17), belonged to the Alpha Phi Alpha fraternity, founded and presided over the Pitt Lyceum, and served as secretary for the International Polity Club. In 1919 he was awarded his Bachelors from the University of Pittsburgh after serving in World War I. Later, Mr. Florence would earn his Masters from the University of Pittsburgh and start, though never finish, post-graduate studies at Harvard University. His teaching and administrative positions took him to Virginia Normal and Industrial Institute (present day Virginia State University), Lincoln University – Missouri, and Virginia Union University, all historically Black colleges.
Custodial History
Ervin Dyer is an award winning journalist for the Pitt Magazine whose articles have also been published in the Pittsburgh Post-Gazette and Pittsburgh Tribune-Review. The papers came into his possession from a variety of sources, including the California Historical Society, Virginia Union University, and Ms. Barbary Grey, a former student of Charles Florence who bought the former Florence family home in Richmond, Va. in 1982; the home likely contained many of the items in the collection.
Scope and Content Notes
The Florence Family papers document the educational and professional activities of Virginia Florence and Charles Florence, both graduates of the University of Pittsburgh. The papers consist of a scrapbook, a dance card, handbooks, a diary, newspaper clippings, postcards, greeting cards, photographs, a magazine article, census records, and obituaries. Also included in the papers are research materials used by Ervin Dyer to complete articles on Charles Florence's participation on the debate team at Pitt.
Ethnic groups; Women; Education; African American universities and colleges; Universities and colleges -- United States; Education, Higher -- United States; African American women librarians; African American educators; Correspondence; Postcards; Photographs; Clippings (Information artifacts); Scrapbooks; Florence, Virginia Proctor Powell; University of Pittsburgh -- Alumni and alumnae; Dyer, Ervin; Florence, Charles W.
- Virginia Proctor Powell Florence, I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series contains Virginia Proctor Powell Florence's papers and consists of three folders. The Fifth Avenue High School scrapbook contains several photographs, handwritten notes from classmates, a dried rose, invitation to an honor's society gathering, and newspaper clippings. The folder entitled "handbook" includes a small pocket style book of essays by Maurice Maesterlinck. Folder three contains material related to VPPF's time as a student at Oberlin College in Ohio and includes a framed print of the Oberlin College Student Creed and a dance card.
  - Fifth Avenue High School Scrapbook, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Handbook, Women and Four other Essays by Maurice Maeterlinck, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Oberlin College, Student Creed & Dance Card, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Charles Florence, II.
  The Charles Florence series consists of eight folders of material related to CF's personal and professional life. The materials consists of the newspaper clippings from the Brownsville telegraph including a column titled "That Was Brownsville"; a photocopy of Charles Florence's grade transcript from Southwestern State Normal School (now California University of Pennsylvania); his calling card and day journal from 1917 during his residence in Pittsburgh, a transcription of the journal by Ervin Dyer is also included, correspondence postcards which date from 1919 to 1951 (arranged by the date stamp on the cards to replicate the order in which Mr. Florence received the postcards); a Lincoln University (Jefferson City, Missouri), Student Handbook from the 1933-1934 academic year; two souvenir postcards books and two individual post cards bought by Charles Florence to commemorate events in his life. The "Paris" postcard book which was likely bought in France during Florence's tour of duty in Europe may have been given to him by Lieutenant Donald Jefferson, a classmate and fellow veteran from Pittsburgh. Also included are commencement programs, yearbooks, a notice announcing a visiting lecturer from Japan all from Florence's time spent at Storer College. The University of Pittsburgh folder contains photocopies of transcripts from both Florence's undergraduate and graduate studies, commencement programs from his undergraduate years, and an invitation to a meeting held by the Alpha Phi Alpha Fraternity of which Charles Florence was a member. In the final folder is letter from the Virginia Normal and Industrial Institute which included a job offer for what would become Charles Florence first professional teaching position.
  - Brownsville Telegraph Newspaper Clippings, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Calling Card and Pocket Journal, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Postcards & Greeting Cards, 1919-1951 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - California University of Pennsylvania, undated (Box 1, Folder 6a)
  - Lincoln University - Missouri, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Souvenir Postcards, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Storer College, 1908-1910 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - University of Pittsburgh, 1915-1919 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Virginia Normal and Industrial Institute, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Photographs, 1910-1965; III.
  This series of photographs represent a span a period of over fifty years not including a political pamphlet which dates from the late 1990's. The photographs include images of Charles Florence and Virginia Proctor Powell Florence together and separate. Also included is a folder which contains exterior photographs of the Florence family homes in Brownsville, PA and Richmond, VA. Old Memorial Hall, on the Lincoln University Campus. Also included are several photographs of African-American men and women whose identities we're unable to be verified at the time of processing.
  - Charles Florence, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Charles and Virginia Florence, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Charles Florence and Eric Crabtree, c 1965 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Florence Family Houses, c 1940s (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Old Memorial Hall, Lincoln University, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Unidentified Women, 1910-1916 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Unidentified Man(possibly Donald Jefferson), undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Virginia Proctor Powell Florence, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Ervin Dyer Research Materials, IV.
  This series contains four folders of research materials that Ervin Dyer used to complete his article entitled, "The Great Debater" in the Summer 2008 issue of Pitt Magazine on Charles Florence. The series includes, a copy of Pitt Magazine, photocopied census records related to the Florence family, correspondence with the California Area Historical Society, and photocopied death notices, obituaries, and death certificates of members of the Florence family.
  - Pitt Magazine Article, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Photocopied Census Records for 1900, 1910, 1920, 1930, ca. 2005-2009 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 2008-2009 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Photocopied Death Notices and Obituaries, ca. 2005 - 2008 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Oversized Materials, V.
  This series contains oversized materials include full newspapers from Storer College, the University of Pittsburgh and a photographic reproduction, possibly of Storer College faculty and students.
  - Storer College, Storer Record, 1909-1915 (Box 1, Drawer 12-6, Folder 1)
  - University of Pittsburgh, Pitt Weekly, 1915-1917 (Box 1, Drawer 12-6, Folder 2)
  - Photographic Reproduction of a group of men with American Flags-original from ca. 1910-1915, ca. 2005-2008 (Box 1, Drawer 12-6, Folder 3)